Gianpaolo Macario - Curriculum Vitae

Last update: 2014-05-19

Contact Details

Email	gmacario@gmail.com
Homepage	http://gmacario.github.io/
LinkedIn Profile	http://it.linkedin.com/in/gmacario/

Summary

As a result of a number of successful projects and experiences I developed good problem solving capabilities and attitudes to quickly be proficient on emerging software technologies.

Goals: To engage in challenging projects based on innovative technologies with potential high returns to the organization.

Specialties: Software Architecture, Open Source Software Development Process, Project Management, Customer Relationship.

Technologies: Automotive Infotainment, Embedded Systems, Embedded Linux, Eclipse, UML

Professional Experience

September 2012-Present: Mentor Graphics, Embedded Software Division

Senior Member, Technical Staff of the Linux Services team - covering the following roles:

- Pre-sales: Architect responsible for the technical proposal during the offer phase
- Delivery: Consultant and technical advisor to leading Automotive OEMs and Tier-1s on both platform and product IVI development projects.

January 2012-Present: GENIVI Alliance. Representing the mother company inside GENIVI covering the following roles:

- Architect of the System Infrastructure Expert Group (SI-EG)
- Voting Member of the System Architecture Team (SAT)
- Voting Member of the Compliance Team

June 2006-August 2012: Magneti Marelli Electronic Systems - Venaria Reale (TO).

- July 2008: Appointed Software Platform Leader for the development and productization of the new Linux-based platform for MMSE infotainment products.
- October 2007: Took responsibility of the MM team tasked of the development and integration of an A-Sample unit for the next generation of infotainment systems for a top German car maker. The product was developed on a reference hardware design provided by a lead US Silicon Vendor, with a production-grade Embedded Linux distribution and third-party middleware. MM activities focused on application development, system integration and validation. The brilliant results of this activity influenced the decision of MM and the partners to move on to the productization phase.
- October 2006: Technical Leader in a joint project together with Telecom Italia to develop and deploy telematics services in the automotive space.

July 2005-May 2006: Comau S.p.A. - Grugliasco (TO). ICT Manager

- After the termination of the Joint Venture between IBM and Fiat I was reassigned to the ICT Department of the Robotics Business Unit of Comau, where I was responsible of the operations and the evolutive maintenance of an enterprise application for Product Lifecycle Management.
- Related products and technologies: MatrixOne eMatrix, BEA WebLogic, Oracle, J2EE, XML.

April 2002-June 2005: GlobalValue (an IBM and Fiat Company) - Torino. Senior Consultant - Telematics and Wireless Solutions

- Provided training and consulting to an European automotive Tier-1 Supplier and automotive Research
 Center on embedded software development, Linux and Java for an innovative telematics project developed
 within the EU 6th Framework Programme.
 Specific tasks being carried out: porting and optimization of an Embedded Linux distribution to custom
 target (ARM architecture), debug and adaptation of the Linux Bluetooth stack for a non-standard Bluetooth
 adapter, porting of the IBM J9 Embedded Java Virtual Machine.
- Worked jointly with an international IBM team (US, Korea, France) on a global telematics project for a leading Korean car manufacturer. Developed API, reference implementation software (J2ME, SWT) and Eclipse plugins; organized the technology transfer workshop to the customer.
- Worked as instructor during a few workshops (US, Germany) about the IBM RFID middleware solution organized for J2ME/J2EE architects and developers.
 Prepared workshop material and exercises, assisted and mentored students on IBM RFID Edge product and tooling.
- Worked as technical support of GlobalValue and IBM Client Executives on several opportunities involving
 wireless and telematics technologies. Organized technical meeting and workshops with customers,
 identified solution and worked on the architecture and the project sizing.
- In cooperation with IBM developed a feasibility study and a pre-production pilot of a service of Mobile Office Synchronization between etherogeneous mobile devices (PDAs, Smart Phones, etc.) and corporate servers via GPRS. The infrastructure was based on IBM middleware (WEA, WECM, etc.)
- Developed the opportunity and achieved contract with the Research Center of an Italian Car Manufacturer to adopt IBM middleware (J2ME, OSGi) for an in-vehicle telematics project partly sponsored by the European Community.

February 1998-March 2002: <u>Magneti Marelli Sistemi Elettronici</u> - Venaria Reale (TO). Senior System Engineer

- Ported and configured Embedded Linux on custom target hardware (x86 and Hitachi SH architectures).
- Designed the software architecture and led a team of developers to prototype a Java+OSGi-based invehicle telematics system running on production-grade hardware (Connect platform).
- Transferred technology and knowledge to company on: Open Standards, Internet Protocols, Web, WAP, Java, and Real-Time Operating Systems.

November 1992-January 1998: Società di Elettronica per l'Automazione (SEPA) - Torino. Design Engineer

• Responsible for RTOS porting and firmware design to custom hardware.

June 1992-July 1992: Hewlett-Packard Laboratories - Palo Alto, California. Summer Stage Intern

• Transferred Software Engineering Technology developed at Politecnico di Torino to HP Laboratories Database Department (languages: C, C++).

Foreign Languages

- English: very good in writing and speaking.
 Frequent business trips to United States and across Europe.
 Achieved Top Level of the Shenker Method (lesson 100/100) at The Shenker Institute of Turin.
- French: writing good, speaking sufficient (able to follow-up a conversation)
- · German: basic

Education

1985-1992: Politecnico di Torino - Torino

- Admitted to third year of "Dottorato di Ricerca in Ingegneria Informatica e dei Sistemi" (Italian Ph.D.)
- Graduated in 1989 (110/110 Summa Cum Laude) in Electronics Engineering.

1981-1985: Liceo Scientifico G.Peano - Cuneo

• Diploma di Maturità Scientifica (60/60)

Personal Interests

- Internet, skiing, cycling, backpacking, attending kids on weekends...
- · Linux advanced user since 1993 (Linux kernel 0.99).
- Open Source hacker whenever time permits: My profile on Ohloh